This was once the site of a Teraskin-Indian community.
Today, the streets, shops, and dwellings of more than 500 people lie buried beneath lava.
A short distance away, a steep-sided cinder cone marks
the spot where Paricutín volcano heaved rock and ash from the earth for a period of 9 years.
In 1943 thick sticky lava, driven by large volumes of gas
exploded out of Paricutín's vents.
Material that was blasted into the air to cool and solidify.
Much of it fell around the vent, forming a cone-shaped mountain of cinders
The rest, carried by wind, spread a choking blanket of ash and dust over an area of 25 square kilometers.
At night, the fiery glow of falling cinders quickly showed the cone building,
while the lava that buried the village poured from several small vents around the base of the new mountain.
Paricutín erupted from a place where no volcano had been before.
Now it is dormant (extinct/inactive).
It's activity seems to have come to an end.
But we know some volcanos have remained inactive for hundreds, even thousands, of years
and then unexpectedly erupted again.